Register of the Eugene Lyons Papers 1919-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
- PAMPHLET FILE, 1929-1976
  - Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA)
    - Stalin, Joseph
      - Stalin's Speeches on the American Communist Party, Central Committee of the CPUSA, New York, 1929 (Folder 15)
      - The World Situation, The Internal and International Position of the Soviet Union, International Publishers, New York, 1934 (Folder 16)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1928-1967
  - Look, issue for with series of articles on the Soviet Union. Includes annotations and notes by Eugene Lyons., October 3, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook on Eugene Lyons' career, Clippings., 1937-38.
  - Estampas de la Revolucion Espanola, 19 Julio de 1936, Barcelona, Spain, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Scrapbooks on Eugene Lyons' career. Clippings and letters.
    - 1928-1938
    - 1930-1951
- MEMORABILIA
  - Plaques (Box 20)
    - Freedom Foundation at Valley Forge plaque, 1971
    - Hungarian Freedom Fighters Federation plaque, 1966
  - Horseshoe from the blacksmith shop at the Herbert Hoover National Historic Site, West Branch, Iowa
  - Nameplate
- SOUND RECORDINGS (PHONORECORDS)
  - 13 sound recordings of speeches by E. Lyons and Daniel Lyons relating to conditions and events in the Soviet Union Included is a Radio Liberty program on Boris Pasternak., 1917-1975.
    - Speak Up, America! sound recording, undated
      Lyons asks Americans to see if they are "one of Stalin's suckers," too tolerate of communist "infiltration" in their society. He says the communists make lies noble means of recruitment, quoting Lenin. He is particularly critical of innocence clubs, such as the American Youth Congress, and other benign-seeming organizations to appeal to "liberals" and "idealists." Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002251
    - "Radio Liberation Presents Boris Pasternak: Selections from Broadcasts to the Soviet Union," October 1958
      Access
      Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0012375
      Exerpts of Radio Liberation broadcasts from October 23-29, 1958. Includes readings from the diary of Alexander Afinogenov, Boris Pasternak's recollections of Leo Tolstoy and Vladimir Mayakovsky, a review of Pasternak's literary career, and passages from 'Doctor Zhivago'. Radio Liberation's name was changed to Radio Liberty in 1959.
      - Letter from Howland H. Sargeant, 9 April 1959 (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - "Radio Liberation Presents Boris Pasternak," transcript, October 1958 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - A Radio Liberation Production
      50th Anniversary of the Russian Revolution of 1905
      Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0012377
    - Sound recording of American Broadcasting Company radio program, 1956 February 19
      Lyons speaks about how communist countries are attempting to reacquire expatriates in the free world and the reaction of Europeans when familiar with both freedom and communism. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002253
    - Sound recording of Eugene Lyons speaking about communism in Hollywood, undated
      Eugene Lyons speaks about communist influence in the Hollywood and America. He explains how communists use subversive organizations with liberal names to convert Americans. He further describes how American communists are under the control of Moscow, citing how the words of chants changed during World War II depending on how German-Soviet relations were doing. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002254
    - Sound recording of American Broadcasting Company radio program, 1956 March 11
      General note
      Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002255
    - Sound recording of Eugene Lyons speaking about communism in Hollywood, undated
      Content sounds very similar to other sound recording bearing this title. Nola Recording Studios inner label. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002256
    - Sound recording of Air Mail Personal interview with Marjorie Silver, undated
      Marjorie Silver interviews Eugene Lyons for Air Mail Personal. They speak about Lyons' history as well as his work with refugee camps in Europe. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002257
    - Sound recording of Eugene Lyons speaking about communism, 1948 July 31
      Lyons recounts the actions of communists in America, including political parties and spying. He believes communists and their unknowing sympathizers hide behind the freedoms of speech and press. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0002805
    - Letter to a Young American Pole sound recording, undated
      Lyons addresses a young Pole, Michael, on what a Polish ethnicity means to an American citizen, and how oppressions in both countries are related. 2 discs. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0004366
- SOUND RECORDING (CASSETTE TAPE)
  - Sound recording of Colonel James E. Norwood speech: Victory Over Communism: What You Can Do to Make It Happen, March 18, 1971
    Audio cassette 1. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007847
- SOUND RECORDINGS (PHONOTAPES), 1963-1968
  - Sound recording of Eugene Lyons speech to the Milwaukee Forum, undated
    Lyons delivers a speech highly critical of the Soviet Union and communism. He looks at conditions in the nation, why its people are not supportive of it, and why Americans look up to it or apologize for it. Tape 1. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007835
  - Sound recording of Eugene Lyons speech: Appropriate Attitudes to Allies and Dr. Schwarz speech: The Communist Appeal to the Intellectual, October 28, 1963 October 28, 1963
    Part 1: Lyons "Appropriate Attitudes to Allies and Enemies," Indianapolis. In a prepared speech, Lyons reviews America's relationship with the Soviet Union and communism. He is harshly critical of detente and appeasement, believing that America cannot coexist with the Soviet Union. He believes communism is inherently evil.
    Part 2: Schwarz "The Communist Appeal to the Intellectual." Schwarz analyzes who is a communist and how they got that way. In doing so, he looks at why communism has an appeal to students. Tape 2. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007836
  - Sound recording of Herbert Hoover: Biography in Sound, June 8, 1964
    This is a non-English-language biography of U.S. President Herbert Hoover. Tape 3. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007840
  - Sound recording of the Big Lie radio program, April 29, 1967
    The Mutual Broadcasting System produced this program about Svetlana Alliluyeva. It includes clips of a Svetlana press conference and commentary by Eugene Lyons. It was recorded on 27 April 1967 and broadcast two days later. Tape 4. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007841
  - Sound recording of the Winter Park University Club pow wow meeting, March 8, 1968
    Eugene Lyons delivers a speech, "Worker's Paradise Lost," to the Winter Park University Club in Winter Park, Florida. Tape 5. Use copy reference number: 85006_a_0007842
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - 91 prints depicting E. Lyons at various stages of his life, undated (Envelope A-C)
  - 6 prints of E. Lyons and his wife, Billy, undated (Envelope D)
  - 30 prints of the Lyons family and friends, undated (Envelope E)
  - 12 prints depicting E. Lyons at various speaking engagements, undated (Envelope F)
  - 14 prints depicting E. Lyons with individuals and groups, undated (Envelope G)
  - 6 prints of E. Lyons' books on display, undated (Envelope H)
  - 10 prints of various individuals and groups, undated (Envelope I)
  - 6 prints of David Sarnoff, undated (Envelope J)
  - 118 prints of E. Lyons with the Zellerbach Commission on the European Refugee Situation tour of Europe, October 15 - November 1, 1957 (Album fK)
  - 348 prints of E. Lyons, his wife and family, and others, 1920-1980 (Album fL)